Guide to the Carl Louis Mortison Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Carl Louis Mortison papers
1937-1941
MS 1232
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3
(4 folios)
Drawings, photographs and newspaper clippings relating to the trial of Mayor T. Frank Hayes of Waterbury, Conn. together with a number of city officials for conspiracy. The Mortison cartoons appeared in the Waterbury Republican and the Waterbury American. The three scrapbooks contain reproductions of the Mortison cartoons and Pulitzer prize-winning stories from these newspapers on the two year trial together with annotations by Mortison. These have been filmed and discarded.
Mortison, Carl Louis, d. 1963
Existence and Location of Copies
Scrapbooks are available on microfilm (291 frames on 1 reel, 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM135.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Carl L. Mortison, June 1944.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Carl Louis Mortison Papers consists mostly of political cartoons Mortison drew for the Waterbury Republican and the Waterbury American in the years 1937-1939. They form a running commentary on the trial of Mayor T. Frank Hayes and a number of city officials for conspiracy – a trial whicih one clipping calls "the longest criminal trial in the history of the state." The Waterbury newspapers were awarded a Pulitzer prize for their part in exposing the scandal. The collection also contains related photographs and clippings.
Mortison's original cartoons are stored in four folios, listed on the following page. Two scrapbooks of the published cartoons, and one scrapbook of other clippings, have been filmed (HM Film 135) and destroyed.
The papers came to Yale from Mortison in 1944. Mortison died in 1963.
The Waterbury American; The Waterbury Republican; Political corruption -- Connecticut -- Waterbury; Connecticut; United States -- Politics and government; Waterbury (Conn.) -- Politics and government; Cartoonists; Hayes, T. Frank; Mortison, Carl Louis, d. 1963
- Inventory
  - Photographs removed from scrapbooks, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Cartoons (originals)
    - 1938 Jan-Jun, 1938 January-June (Box 2)
    - 1938 Jul-Dec, 1938 July-December (Box 3)
    - 1939 Jan-Aug, 1939 January-August (Box 4)
- Microfilm HM 135, 1937-1943
  Scope and Contents
  HM Film 135 records three scrapbooks kept by Mortison. The first two contain the printed copies of his cartoons, clipped from the Waterbury newspapers, with some photographs and other clippings; the third contains clippings about the trial. A few pages contain Mortison's later annotations, so that the inclusive dates for the film are 1937-1943.
  - Cartoons (clippings)
    - Volume 1, 1937 December-1938 June (Box 1)
    - Volume 2, 1938 June-1939 August (Box 1)
    - Volume 3, Clippings, 1938 January-Jul, 1939 August-November, 1941 November (Box 1)